好的…给你
Hey, okay .. now..
我们再来做一遍
let's go again.
-这是9号吗? -是的,这是9号,有一对明眸
Which one's this, number9? -Yeah, number 9.  Bright eyes.
你在看吗?
Are you watching this?
简直不可思议!
This, this is unbelieveable.
天啊!
Oh, my God.
-移动了多少次? -20
How many moves was that? -20.
最好的一回是15次 你给了它什么?
The perfect score is 15. God, what, what are you giving her?
把它的录像带给我!
Hey, give me that video!
9号黑猩猩,只打了一剂
Chimp number 9, just one dose.
-我晚点再见你? -我们可以开始了
Couldn't I see you later? -We're good to go.
我再回你!  谢谢,拜拜!
I'm going to call you back. Yeah, all right.  Thanks, Bye.
112型,起作用了
112, it works.
-只在一个灵长类身上? -这就是我们需要的
On just the one primate? -One is all we need.
整体的意识复苏
Full cognitive recovery.
-我们准备好了 -这会不会太轻率了?
We're ready.
Look, are you sure you're not rushing this?
我都为这个忙了五年半了
I've been working on this for five and a half years.
数据上没问题 我们准备好了,史蒂芬
The data is clear. We're ready, Steven.
现在我需要的是你批准进行人体试验
All I need is your approval for human trials.
那个你得需要老板的批准
Oh, for this, you're going to need the Board's approval.
那将会追加投入很多的钱,威尔
There's a lot of money riding on this, Will.
-你只有一次机会 -一次就够了
You only get one shot. -One shot is all I need.
[sighs]
好吧,但是我需要看完所有的文件资料
All right. I'll need to see all the research.
就这么定了!
You got it!
-还有… -什么?
Oh, and Will .. -Yeah?
把你的个人情绪排除在外
Keep your personal emotions out of it.
这些投资的人只看重结果不在乎什么梦想
These people invest in results, not dreams.
好的!
Okay!
来见见黑猩猩9号,这个测试叫做“汉诺塔”
Meet chimp 9. Here she's tasking at what is called the Lucas Tower.
规则就是把圆盘从一个柱子 移到另一个柱子上
The object of which is to move the tower from peg to peg
小圆盘上不能放大的 3根柱子间1次只能移1个圆盘
without placing a larger block on top of a smaller block.
不出所料的,它完全被难住了
As expected, she was unable to complete the puzzle at all.
然后我们给它服用了 我们称之为ALZ-112的药物
Then, we gave her what we call, ALZ-112, a gene therapy
一种具有基因治疗效用的 能刺激大脑细胞进行自我修复
that allows the brain to create its own cells in order to repair itself.
在生物学上,这叫做神经发育
In biology, this is called neurogenesis.
在“创世纪”公司 我们称之“老年痴呆症的解药”
Here, at GEN-SYS,
we call it a cure to Alzheimer's.
-丹尼,准备好了吗? -准备好了
Donnie, you get her ready? -She's got stage fright.
确定吗?
Is that what it is?
Hey, ape.
它抓住我的手了!
She's gonna break my arm!
“明眸”,放手!
Bright Eyes! Let go!
你没事吧?
Are you all right?
我们已经做好进入下一阶段的准备
We're ready to move on to the next phase.
进行人体试验
Human trials.
给你,明眸 你最喜欢的水果汽水
Here you go, Bright Eyes. It's your favorite fizzy soda.
丹尼,他已经不肯出来了
Come on, let's go, Donnie.
We should have her downstairs already.
好的,好女孩!
Okay. Good girl!
到这边来
Come on out, girl, that's right.
这是给你的
That's for you.
我抓住它了!
Got her!
天啊!
Jesus!
丹尼打开笼子!
Donnie, open the cage! Open up! Open up!
尝尝这个!
Going to sedate her!
-不不! -守住门口!
No, no! -Get the door!
不,不!赶快控制住!
No, no! Hold it! Now!
快去帮忙!丹尼!起来
Call help! Donnie, Donnie!
ALZ-112在绝对没有副作用,除了一点
There have been absolutely no side effects associated
with 112, with one exception.
不知何故
For some reason,
黑猩猩的瞳孔中闪现绿光
the chimps irises exhibit flecks of green.
就好像这个黑猩猩9号,昵称是“明眸”
Actually, we first noticed it in chimp 9,
hence her nickname, Bright Eyes.
我们一会带过来让大家看看
You'll see when we bring her in.
躲开!
Move!
理论上,这种药物可以被用作
In theory, this therapy can be used
治疗大部分的脑疾病
to treat a wide range of brain disorders.
当然也会有范围
It's virtually limitless.
以及巨大的盈利潜力
As are the potential profits.
这也就是我们的自信 你们会加大投资来支持人体试验
which is why we are confident that
you will vote to approve human trials.
不,不!
No, no, no!
雅各先生 雅各先生,我请求你别这么做
Mr. Jacobs, Mr. Jacobs I am begging you,
I am begging you, not to do this.
Look, it costs a small fortune to
现在只有一丁点资金来维持实验室运转
run lab workups on all of those chimps
only to tell me what I already know,
对于这些黑猩猩,你就讲一些我不知道的
that they are contaminated.
There are lives at stake here.
这里不适合养它们
These, these are animals with personalities,
这些动物都很有个性,所以挑剔环境
with attachments.
Attachments? -Yeah.
-挑剔环境? -是的
I run a a business, not a petting zoo.
我搞的是生意,不是动物园
Find the most cost effective way to put those apes down.
把这些猴子都安乐死了
我做不到
I can't do that.
You're the chimp handler.
你是它们的管理者,解决这个问题
Handle it.
Steven!
史蒂芬!
Well, that was fun!
-哦那可真有趣! -他们拿走了112药物
They've taken the 112.
Board has rejected your proposal.
委员会拒绝了你的提案 他们将把资金注入其他的计划
They've chosen to advance other programs.
Well, there must be something that you can do.
-一定有什么你能做到 -有啊,我被炒鱿鱼吧
Yes. There is, I could fire you.
Believe me, we talked about it.
相信我,我跟他们谈过了
We have five years of conclusive data.
我们花了五年时间来建立那些数据
Parade all the data you want,
我了解你多么重视那些数据
you will never convince anyone to invest another dime.
但是你永远无法说服别人投入资金了
This drug has the potential to save lives!
这项成果能拯救生命!
Bankrupt this company, more like.
这会是公司所在意的吗
I swear, you know everything about the human brain
我怀疑,你懂得人大脑的一切
except the way it works.
除了它是怎么想的
Go back to the drawing board on the 112.
回到112的设计阶段
Start again in molecular development.
重新开始研制
Find a way to get there before someone else does.
在别人做到之前找到解决方法
And, clean up this mess.
还有打理好这烂摊子
Franklin!
富兰克林!
It's very small. She must have been
这是小的,她被带来时怀孕了
pregnant when we brought her in.
So that's why ..
所以这就是为什么… 它不具有侵略性而是在保护孩子
She wasn't being aggressive. She was just being protective.
She thought we were going to hurt her baby.
它以为我们要伤害孩子
I would take it myself,
我想带着它
but my brother-in-law works for security. He'd rat me out in a seceond.
但是我哥哥在保卫部工作,他绝对不会容忍
What, you want me to take it home?
你想让我带它回家? 我不会照顾猴子
I can't take care of a monkey.
He's not a monkey! He's an ape. -Franklin ..
-它不是猴子!它是只猿… -富兰克林…
You know, it's just for a couple days until
就一些时日,然后我会找到安全的地方
I find a sanctuary.  That's all I need.
Franklin, no!
富兰克林,不!
Look, this isn't my responsibility.
这不是我的职责,而且这是公司的财产
This, this is company property.
Okay ..
好吧…
I tell you what, Doc.
想想吧,博士
Jacobs made me put down the other 12.
雅各让我把剩余12只安乐死
I'm done.
我做完了
Be my guest.
请便
雅图在线 高清点播
yatu.tv | yatour.cn 2004~2011
Hey! -Oh, hi.
嘿 !
You look beat. -Yeah. How's he doing?
-你一脸倦容 -他在做什么?
Well, he has good days and bad days.
他就好一天坏一天
Today, not so good, although he
今天状态好得朗诵莎士比亚呢
has been quoting Shakespeare.
Oh, you got a pet?
-你买了个宠物? -只是个临时房客
Uh, it's just a temporary house guest.
Well, maybe that'll be good for him.
也许不错呢
Good night!
晚安!
[discordant piano playing]
Hi, Dad!
嗨,老爸!
Dad?
爸?
Will! I didn't hear you come in.
威尔 嘿!我没听到你进来
Today's the day, right?
就是今天,对吧?
You thought I'd forget?
你以为我忘了吧? 你今天有个重要试验,对吧?
You have a big test today, right?
Chemistry?
化学的?
Hey, Dad ..
爸…
You want to see something? -What?
-想看看吗? -什么?
What is that? Is he injured?
-它受伤了? -不,我想那是胎记
No, I think that's a birthmark.
"As for Caesar, kneel down, kneel down and wonder!"
“可是对于凯撒,他只有跪伏惊叹的份” （出自莎士比亚）
Yeah, don't get too attached.
别贴上了
He's a cute little guy, isn't he?
太有趣了
Where's my car keys?
我车钥匙哪里去了?
My car keys, where'd you put 'em?
我车钥匙你放哪里了?
Dad, .. you a, you don't drive anymore.
爸,你不能再开车了
I know that.
我知道
Here ..
这里…
Why don't you feed him. Can you do that?
-喂它,你能做吗? -当然能
Of course, I can..
Will! .. Look at this!
威尔!看啊!
How old is he? Like, a day old? Two days old?
-它多大了?一天,两天? -是的…
Yeah ..
He's a smart one, isn't he?
它真聪明,是不是? 该取个什么名字呢?
What are you going to name him?
I do not know ..
我不知道…
Three years later
三天后
Right away, Caesar displayed signs of intelligence heightened intelligence,
很快,凯撒展现出高速增长的智力
so I kept him.   And, brought my work home.
所以我把工作转移到了家里
By 18 months, Caesar was signing up to 24 words.
18个月凯撒已经学会了24个单词
By age two, Caesar completing puzzles and models
两岁的时候凯撒已经完成了专为
designed for children eight years and up.
八岁以上儿童设计的模拟教学
At age three,
三岁时
Caesar continues to show cognative skills
凯撒继续证明着它已经
that far exceed that of his human counterpart.
远远超过了人类的成长速度
Home .. home.
家
He completed the Lucas Tower in 15 moves, a perfect score.
它用15步完成了汉诺塔,完美的记录
I maintain my hypothesis that: A. The green in his eyes indicate
我假设它的绿眼特征
that the ALZ-112 was passed genetically from mother to son
是由母亲留给儿子的基因 含有ALZ-112药物造成
and, B. That in the absence of damaged cells that need to be replacing
而且没有需要更换的受损细胞
the drug in his system has radically boosted healthy brain functioning.
药物使得体内的增加的细胞健康的运行
And, ..
以及,国际象棋玩得很好…
he plays chess pretty well.
[shouting]
Dad!
爸爸!
I'm sorry. -I can't do this, anymore.
-对不起 -我没法跟他待在一起了
He belongs in a home.
他应该去疯人院 这里容不下他
This is no way for him to live.
No way to live?
没法活了吗?
I broke my lamp ..
我把灯打碎了…
It'll make you better, Dad.
你会好起来的,爸爸
[Shhh..]
Dad!
爸爸!
[exuberant piano playing]
Todd, come inside for breakfast.
陶德,进屋来吃饭
I'll need to keep track of what I take from the lab,
我必须带你到实验室去
although I don't see you needing more than one treatment a month.
而且我认为你每个月需要的剂量不止一管
Something amazing has happened!
太令人惊奇了!
I'll need a blood test, a scan and the dosage ..
我需要做测试,扫描还有剂量的…
carefully monitored.
必须密切留意你,若是你想溜出去…
Now, if I can sneak ..
Will!  I'm not sick, anymore!
威尔!我病好了!
It was nothing, Dad.
-没那回事,爸 -凯撒在哪里?我要见凯撒
Ceasar.  Where's Caesar? I want to see him.
Caesar!
凯撒!
He can't have gone far.
它不会走太远的
Caesar!
凯撒!
Daddy!
爸爸!
Caesar!
凯撒!
Get out of here! Get out!
离开那里!滚开!
Get out!
滚开!
Hey, hey, hey .. Enough! Enough!
够了!
It doesn't matter what you do.
什么毛病啊?
If I catch that animal anywhere near my house or my kids, again ..
如果再让这动物靠近我的房子或者孩子…
He's not dangerous.
-它不是危险的! -不会再发生了
It won't happen again.
Damn right, it won't!
记住了!
Come on, Dad. -He, he just wanted to play.
-走吧,爸 -它只是想玩耍
Stay in the house! Daddy's got you.
待在家里就好
I told you not to go out without us.
我跟你讲过没我们在不要出门
It's okay ..
没事了…
How bad is it?
伤的重吗?
I do not know.
我不知道
He likes you. -Uh, huh.
它喜欢你
Don't worry. It'll be over soon.
别担心,很快就给你治疗了
Then, we can go get a treat.
I'm thinking, ice cream.
我在想冰淇淋
Good idea!
好主意!
You taught him to sign?
-它会手语? -一些基本的
Just, handful of things, basic stuff.
What's he saying?
-他说什么? -没什么
Nothing.
So, when do you think we should come back?
-我们什么时候复诊? -不需要的
Well, you won't need to come back.
because, um, the stiches are dissolveable.
没伤到筋骨,只要小心别感染了
I would just say, watch for signs of infection.
Fever .. redness ..
如果发烧或是红肿…
Okay, what's he saying, now?
现在说什么呢?
Um,
well, ..
he thinks that you and I should have dinner together.
它说我们俩应该共进晚餐
(chuckling) I .. know ..
Caesar! Come on!
凯撒!别闹了!
Good to see you, again, Caroline.
很高兴见到你,卡洛琳
You coming, Caesar?
凯撒你来吗?
So, what's your secret?
你有什么秘密?
Oh, I can't take any credit. It's in his genes.
我不能讲太深,都是跟基因有关的
I think you're being very modest.
我认为你很谦虚,真是惊人
He's pretty amazing.
I think you've built a pretty good home for Caesar, here.
我认为你给凯撒造了一个很好的家
You know he won't stay this way for long.
但是不会持续很久
He's going to soon grow into
它很快就会成长为大型强壮的动物
a large, powerful, animal.
Come here!
过来!
How's he been doing?
-你该怎么办? -这个,我想
Okay, I think.
I love chimpanzees.
我喜欢黑猩猩,人们都害怕它们
I'm also afraid of them.
And, it's appropriate to be afraid of them.
其实害怕它们很正常
Caesar will never hurt anyone.
凯撒不会伤害任何人
He's happy here.
快点下来!
Yeah, I see that.
我能明白那些
We can at least give him some open space?
-你可以给它一些开放的空间? -是啊,应该是个好主意
-Yeah. That would prpbably be a good idea.
I know a place right across the bridge,
我知道跨过大桥有个地方,一片红杉森林 一个人间仙境
the Redwoods.  It's a paradise.
Come on!
来吧!
Come here.
来这边
Doesn't need a leash! He'll be fine. Come on!
它不需要皮绳!它没事的!过来
Just to be safe. -Come on, Caesar!
-只是以防万一 -来吧,凯撒!
It's the redwoods.
这些是红杉树!
Caesar!
凯撒!
All right.
If I take this off you can not leave my sight.
我把这个除去,你不能离开我的视线
I'll never find you again.
不然我们就找不到你了
Okay.
好了
What's this? -What's he doing?
-这是什么? -他在干什么?
I don't believe that! -What?
-我简直不敢相信! -什么?
He's asking your permission.
它在请求你的许可
It's a supplicating gesture.
这是一个祈愿的姿势
It's okay.
没关系的
Come on, Caesar! Off you go!
去吧,凯撒!快去吧!
Look at him go!
看它多开心!
Caesar!
凯撒!
Caesar!! -Caesar!!
Caesar!
凯撒!
There you are ..
你在这…
Caesar!
凯撒!
Come on, Caesar, climb!
去吧,凯撒,爬上去!
Go higher!
爬的高高的!
Climb!
用力爬!
Be careful!
小心点!
Caesar, be careful!
凯撒,小心点!
FIVE YEARS LATER
五年后
Hi!
嘿!
What's going on, buddy?
怎么了?
Give some love.
Come on, honey.
来吧,宝贝
Is that a chimpanzee?
那是一只猩猩吗?
[dog snarls & barks]
Come on!
别闹!
走吧!
[Caesar snarls back at dog]
[dog whimpers]
Caesar! .. Caesar!
凯撒!走吧!
Come on!
It's all right. Come on.
不要紧的,走吧
Come on!
走吧!
Let's go.
Are you getting in?
不进去吗?凯撒…
Caesar ..
You okay, pal?
你还好吧,伙计?
Are you pet? .. No.
你是宠物吗? 不,你不是
You're not a pet.
I am your father.
我是你父亲
What is Caesar?
你说是不是?
Okay ..
好吧…
Caesar, this is where I work.
凯撒,这是我工作的地方 也是你出生的地方
This is were you were born.
Your mother was here with other chimpanzees.
你妈妈当时和其他的猿一起在这里
But she's not here, anymore ..
但是她不在这里了,所以…
so ..
.. that's why I took home to live with me.
…我才把你带回家
Yeah.
是的
Your mother's dead.
你母亲死了
The thing is, she was given medicine,
事实是她被注射了药物
like the medicine I give to Charles.
就像我给查尔斯注射的一样
She passed it on to you.
她遗传给了你 所以你才这么聪明
That's why you're so smart.
Let's take him home.
带他回家吧
Come on, explain it to me.
-来吧!给我解释! -好吧
All right.
I snuck him out of the lab to save his life.
我把它偷带出实验室是为了救它
I had no idea that the effects had been transfered vertically from his mother.
我完全不知道它会遗传自它妈妈
But, since then, he's been displaying incredible signs intelligence.
自那以后,它显示出了非凡的智力
I designed the 112 to repair, but Caesar's gone way beyond that.
我设计了112-I型号来修复 但是凯撒已经远远超过了那个
Here's his IQ from last year.
这是去年的智商
Since then, it's doubled.
然后现在是双倍了
This is all wrong.
这是个错误,威尔
My father was on gone this drug brought him back.
我父亲险些就走了,而这药把他带回来了
You never saw how bad he was.
你没看见当时有多糟
He has his life again.
And, what about Caesar? -What about him?
-那凯撒呢? -怎么了?
How does he fit in?
-它现在应该在哪里呢? -和我在一起,和我们…
With me, .. with us ..
Listen, ..
听着,我知道这对你很难
I know it has been hard for you,
but you are trying to control things that were never meant to be controlled.
但是你想控制一切本身不想被控制的东西
The 112 works.
-112药物是有用的 -你知道你在说什么吗?
Do you realize how you sound?
All I'm saying is this is a good thing.
没有比这更好的了
Caesar's proof of that.
凯撒是活生生的证明,就像我父亲一样
So's my father.
Caesar, eat your food.
凯撒吃饭
Dad, are you okay?
-爸,你还好吧? -是的
Yeah, I'm fine.
Antibodies.
抗体
His system has found a way to fight the 112 virus
免疫系统已经找到了方法来排斥病毒112
so that it can't deliver its therapy.
使它不能生效
My father's disease is going to return with a vengence.
我父亲会病的比之前更重
Stop!
住手!
Stop, right now!
马上住手!
Hey! Get out there! Get out of that car!
滚开那里!离我的车远点!
What the hell are you doing? Get out of my car!
你在做什么? 我说滚出我的车!
I said, get out of my car!
I'm a pilot! I've got to get to the airport!
我本来要去机场的! 现在我要怎么去?
How am I gonna get there now, huh?
Answer the God-damn question! What were you doing?
回答我!你刚刚在做什么?
I have a car just exactly ..
-我有辆和这差不多的车… -懂了…我报警
I'm done .. the police can handle it.
Stay right there! You aren't going nowhere, mister!
站那里别动! 那里也别去!
You will pay!
你必须赔我修理费!
This is your problem, you make it happen!
这是你的问题,你解决!
.. not through with you! Stay right there!
…哪里也别去!别动!
Caesar, stop!
凯撒,住手!
Daddy!
爸!
Caesar!
凯撒!
It's okay.
没事了
He didn't mean it.
It's okay ..
没事了…
把那东西拿下来!
Hey, hey, take that thing off of him!
把那东西拿下来! 我会带它进去,好吗?
Take that thing off of him!
Look, I'll take him in, okay?
我们奉命行事 我们不能让你那么做
No, he's under court orders. We can't do that.
没关系!准备好了再带它进来吧
It's fine! Let him.
Bring him in when you're ready.
给它时间
Take it off.
多谢!
Thank you!
凯撒!
Caesar, Caesar, Caesar, .. Caesar, Caesar.
你会没事的
Not right now. It's going to be okay.
我们去看看里面有什么,好吗?
Let's just see what it's like inside, okay.
来吧,凯撒
Come on, Caesar.
Let's go.
来吧,相信我
Come on, .. trust me.
没关系
It's okay.
去吧
Go.
-它已经很久没跟其他的猿在一起了 -我们遇到过
He hasn't spent any time with other chimps.
Oh, we're used to that.
一开始会害羞,慢慢就融入一起了
He'll be a little skittish at first, but we'll integrate him.
你会惊讶的发现它适应得有多快
You'd be surprised how quick they adapt.
我们会提供良好的环境 它会生活得很好
We provide a stimulating environment.
He's going to thrive here.
来吧,我们做点书面工作 等下记得锁门
Come, let's do some paperwork.
Make sure you lock that door when you come in.
凯撒!
Caesar!
你会没事的!
You'll be okay!
-一切都会好起来的! -不要害怕
Everything's going to be okay!
Don't be scared.
你现在留在这里
You're going to stay here, now.
-不…现在不能回家 -没关系的
No .. Not going home right now.
It's OK.
时间拖的越长就越难受
The longer you drag out the good-byes,
the harder it is.
等会儿再签
Can I sign that later?
也许现在它会想念你并且想留在你身边
You'll probably miss him more than he'll miss you.
不过离开几个星期就习惯了
You'd best give him a couple of weeks to get used too the place.
Will, we have to go.
威尔,我们得走了
We have to go home.
我很快就回来,好吗?
Coming back soon, okay?
来之前打个电话
Just call ahead, before you do.
这边!
Hey, over here!
我带你出去!
Hey, I can get you out!
过来!这边!
Come on!  Over here!
下来到这边来
Hey, down here.
蠢猴子…
Stupid monkey ..
吵什么?找死啊!
So you? Come on, make it!
调令已经被备案,所以系统中暂时没有
Court order hasn't been filed, so it's not in the system.
一旦通过
Once it comes through,
请90天之后再来
it will take about 90 days before you receive an appeal date.
-90天? -是的,90天
90 days? -Yes, sir, 90 days.
你会被电邮通知
You'll be notified by mail.
这样吧,你回去弄电脑,清掉记录
Here's what's going to happen.
You're going to go back to your computer, you know, shift things around
然后这周内就给我,明白没?
and you're going to get me a date for my appeal, this week, you got it?
我帮不了你
I can't help you.
那就麻烦了,你不做我就不走了
All right, then we have a problem.
Because, I'm not moving until you do.
90天,先生,被通知了就感激吧
90 days, sir. Be thankful you're talking about court dates.
你已经很幸运了
You're lucky they didn't put that animal down.
我保证很快就带它回来,爸
I promised to get him back soon, Dad.
爸?
Dad?
我父亲的免疫系统继续病毒拒绝112
My father's immune system continues to reject the 112 virus,
他遗忘的越来越多
rendering the gene therapy obsolete.
健康状况在恶化,并迅速加重疾病
his health is deteriorating, and the disease is progressing rapidly.
我需要一种更具侵略性的病毒
I need a more aggressive virus strain,
能够更迅速的产生效用
a faster delivery method,
因为这一次…
because at this rate ..
I can't lose them both.
我不能失去他们两个!
I won't lose them both.
-嘿!能谈谈吗? -最好快点,我要去开会
Hi ... Can we talk?
Make it fast.  I've got a meeting.
你领导GEN-SYS公司十年了
The ten years you have been running GEN-SYS,
有多少药物能拯救成千上万的生命?
how many drugs have come down the pipeline that could save millions of lives?
能改变一切?
That could change everything?
-你指什么? -ALZ-112药物
What are you talking about?
The ALZ-112.
你到底怎么了,威尔?
What happened to you, Will?
你曾是这实验室的明星 现在几乎没有容身之地
You used to be the star of this lab. Now, you hardly ever show
当你脱离团队专注于那药物上时
and when you do, you waste your time and that of your team's
fixating on a drug
那个永远绝对不可能再有进展
that, after what happened, is never ever going to get approved.
112药物很危险,威尔,它不好用
The 112 is dangerous, Will,
and it doesn't work.
我用它治好了我父亲,它有用
I treated my father with it.
It does work.
你做了什么?
You did, what?
You did, what!?
他战胜了病魔,正如所料
Beat the disease, like we predicted.
-把他带过来 -这有些复杂
Brilliant.
There's been a complication.
到底是有用还是没用?
Well, does it work or doesn't it?
最终我父亲没能战胜病魔
My father's disease eventually outran the cure.
哦天!
Oh, for goodness sake.
免疫系统产生抗体击败了病毒
The immune system produced antibodies to beat the viral component,
补救措施没有任何效果
but it will work.
我已经开发了一种病毒品种 我相信会更具有侵略性
I've have already developed a virus strain
that I think will be more aggressive.
-你认为? -让我测试一下
You think?
Just, let me test it.
You're wasting my time.
-你在浪费我的时间 -还有!
There's more!
The applications go beyond the disease.
药物治不了老年痴呆症
There are indications that show the therapy can improve cognitive functioning,
有迹象表明治疗可以提高认知功能
memory quality ..
和记忆的质量…
What, what are you saying?
-你现在在说什么? -我父亲不只是恢复了
My father didn't just recover.
He improved.
-还提高了 -你的意思是智力提高了?
You mean, increased intelligence?
It's not conclusive, but yes.
没有根据,但是是的
赶快用黑猩猩做112型的评估测试
I want you, to start testing the revised 112 on chimps, A-S-A-P.
-好的 -我给你你需要的一切,去做吧
Okay.
I'll give you whatever you need, but get started.
Dinner time!
晚饭了!
Great Ape, primate!
气色不错!
Go on, don't you know food when you see it?
吃吧,没见过这样的食物?
You think that's funny, huh?
有趣吗?
I show you something funny!
我告诉你什么叫有趣!
You'll learn who's boss, soon enough.
你会了解谁是你的老大
What about his clothes?
-它还穿着衣服呢? -那又怎么了?
What about 'em?
I don't know .. May cause problems with the other apes.
我不知道…也许会引起疾病
Good!
好!
I counted ten apes, correct?
一共有有十只猩猩,对吧
Yep.
Good.  All the way to the back.
好,都推后面去
You guys are moving really quick on this. What's the big rush?
雅各为什么这么着急做实验?
First day back, you're still complaining.
你第一天回来上班当然疑惑
Koba. Hi, I'm Will.
寇巴,嗨,我是威尔
This one.
就这个
He's very calm.
-它很冷静 -是的
Yeah.
He's been through a whole lot of labs. He knows the drill.
它辗转了很多实验室,了解这些程序
Could I join you, what's our progress.
我想我也来实施过程的监控
Get him prepped.
准备好
Tighten your masks.
戴好面具,113型拿给我
Pass me the 113.
Pulse-ox is good, blood pressure is steady.
脉搏正常,心跳稳定
Perisol delivery, in place.
剂量调试完成
Releasing the 113.
开始释放113型
We have a break!
管道破裂了!
Franklin, get your mask on!
富兰克林,戴上面具!
Got it?
-戴上了? -是的
Yeah.
You okay?
-你还好吗? -是的
Yeah, okay.
Move it!  Let's go!
动一动!
Get up and do some exercises you lazy baboons!
醒醒,运动运动,你们这些懒猩猩!
（雅各）
Intelligence results are remarkable.
智力如预期的增长了
There are no adverse effects.
没有负面影响
Apes have amazingly strong immune systems.
灵长类动物的免疫系统难以置信的强大
All right, keep an eye on him.
-盯紧它 -好的
Okay. [Franklin sneezes]
Sorry about that.
抱歉,它比我更壮
These guys are more resiliant than I am.
Excuse me a second.
请等一下
You seriously injured?
你伤的重吗?
Do you know sign language?
你懂手语?
I worked at the circus.
我以前在马戏团
He's good.
做吧
Be Careful. Humans do not like intelligent apes.
小心,人类不喜欢有智慧的猿猴
今晚会工作到很晚
You're working late tonight.
GEN-SYS公司还需要三个
GEN-SYS needs three more.
嘿,凯撒!
Hey, Caesar!
你受伤了?
Are you hurt?
给我看看
Show me.
凯撒,把手给我,没关系
Caesar, give me your hand. Give me your hand.
有时,新的猴子会很引人瞩目
Sometimes, the new kid on the block gets picked on.
冷静,他们对你做什么了?
Stay calm. What did they do?
我听你胡扯!
That's bullshit!
发生什么了?
What's the problem here?
-我现在就带它走! -没有法院调令不行
I'm taking him out of here, right now.
Not without a court order, you're not.
它已经不是你的了
He's not yours, anymore.
我发誓,如果我发现它病了
I promise, if I find out he's been mistreated in any way,
我一定让这里关门
I'll have this place shut down.
过去…
Go on ..
不,我们现在不能回家 但是我一定带你离开这里,我保证
No.  No, we're not going home, right now.
I'm going to get you out of here, I promise.
相信我
You have to trust me.
-凯撒,相信我,好吗? -这次会客结束了
Caesar, you have to trust me, okay?
I think this visit's over.
相信我,你会没事的
Trust me.
You'll be okay.
动一动!
Come on, move it! Let's go!
-有上百只啊! -就好像一个动物园!
There are hundreds of them! Looks like you're own private zoo!
更像一个监狱
Rather like a prison for hairy dudes.
-它们看电视 -我们管那叫教育
They watch TV?
We call it enrichment.
-这个好可爱!它叫什么? -是科妮莉亚,是母的
Aw, this one's so cute!
What's his name?
Uh, name's Cornelia. It's a she.
[shreek]
-天! -别靠得太近!
Oh, my God!
Don't get too close!
-吓我一跳 -这个大家伙叫莫里斯
This one scared me half to death.
That big guy is called, Maurice.
没意思
It's no fun.
我给你们看点有趣的
Here, I'll show you something fun.
小心哦!
Check this out!
太疯狂了!
It's crazy!
-今天不该你 -下一个就是你!
You shouldn't be in here.
Hey, you're next!
我们走吧,今天不该我值班
Come on, let's go.
We spent too much time in here, as it is.
走吧!
Come on!
-看这只 -那是个令人讨厌的,它觉得自己很特殊
Check out this guy.
Hey, Alan, he's a pain in the ass. He thinks he's special, or something
太酷了!
Freaky!
过来
Hey, come here.
它好像想喝酒
I think he's thinking or something.
天呐,它在做什么! 叫它放手!
Oh, my God, he's got him by the throat!
Let him go!
放手!
Let go!
-你还好吗? -没事
Are you okay?
Yes.
我告诉过你不要靠太近
I told you not to get too close, man.
我们走吧
Come on, guys, let's get out of here.
有些事不必去改变
Some things aren't meant be changed.
你需要去接受
You need to accept that.
Hey!
这里怎么了?
What's going on here?
我们在测试113型,只是…
More 113 trials. We're just prepping ..
不,你们要先去测试寇巴的血样!
Oh, no, we have to analyze Koba's blood work first!
-富兰克林知道的,他在哪里? -他病了两天了
Franklin knows this. Where is he?
He's out sick for two days.
-我没批准进行 -是没
Well, I didn't authorized this.
No!
我批准了
I did.
我们都同意只在一个身上试验
We agreed to test sparingly on one subject.
那一个很惊人!
And, that one subject is stunning!
这是一个病毒 我们不知道用在人身上会有什么影响!
It's a virus. We don't know the human related effects.
这药是管用的,威尔 告诉他,琳达
The drug works, Will.
Tell him, Linda.
首先,寇巴完成了汉诺塔
For starters, Koba scored a perfect 15 on the Lucas Tower.
只用了15步,完美的
Every test result verifies its effectiveness.
所有的测试结果都证实了其效果
-没有测试了! -你在做什么?
No more tests. -What are you ..?
我们需要搞明白我们在这里做什么
Not until we have a better understanding of what we're dealing with.
我会明白的告诉你我们在做什么! 给我点时间
Look, I'll tell you exactly what we do. Look ..
Give us a minute.
打扰一下!把那猴子关回笼子,小心的
Excuse me!   Put the ape back in the cage. Be gentle.
我明白的告诉你我们在做什么
Will, I'll tell you exactly what we're dealing with, here.
我们正在面对我们合作以来
We're dealing with a drug that is worth more
最有价值的药物
than everything else we are developing, combined.
你创造历史,我负责赚钱
You make history,
I make money.
-这回明白了吧? -风险太大了
Isn't that our arrangement? -No! There are risks.
别跟我谈风险
Don't you tell me about risks.
你给你父亲试验中的药物
You give your own father an experimental drug.
我打个电话就能结束你的职业生涯
I could finish your career with one phone call.
省省吧,我不干了
I'll save you the trouble. I quit.
没有你我们一样会继续
We will proceed without you.
你不知道你在干什么 这测试还需要观察
Look .. You do not know what you're doing.
These tests need to be contained.
你不知道这113型会给 人类造成什么样的伤害
You have no idea if the 113 is stable,
what kind of damage it can do to people ..
所以我们才拿猩猩做实验,对吧?
Well, that is why we test it on chimps, .. isn't it?
罗曼医生,我是富兰克林! 我需要跟你谈谈!
Dr. Rodman, it's, me, Franklin! I need to talk to you!
你能来开下门吗?
Can you come to the door?
医生!
Doc! [coughing]
你在做什…
Who the hell are you? [Franklin sneezes on neighbor]
离开这里!
Get out of here!
抱歉!
I'm sorry, .. I'm sorry.
想贿赂我,是吗?
You wouldn't be trying to entrap me, would you?
我不能说我批准了 猩猩不是人类,你懂的
Well, .. I can't say that I approve.
They're not people, you know.
你现在让它走了?
You gonna to let him go or not?
凯撒,过来!
Caesar, .. hey, come on.
来吧,回家
Come on, we're go home.
家!
Home.
来吧,真的走了
Come on, we're really going.
我们离开这里吧!
Let's get out of here.
是的…走吧!
Yeah .. Come on.
凯撒!
Caesar?
我想它更喜欢在这里
I guess he likes it better here with his own kind.
为什么要给饼干?
Why cookies, Rocket?
单独的猩猩…很弱小
A single monkey .. is weak.
团结起来,就变得强大
Monkeys together -a force
猩猩都很蠢的
Monkeys are stupid.
该死的,朗尼 你又溜到中庭去了!
Damn it, Rodney,
You leave the hose out in the atrium, again?
这里? 没!
What?   No!
起来啦!
Come on!  Let's go.
动一动,起床了!
Come on, Get up!
发射的八个月之后
[On TV] Eight months after its launch,
第一次载人太空船飞向火星…
Earth's first manned space flight to Mars ..
我发誓,道奇!我没撒谎
I ain't dodging. I'm telling the truth.
要不是你偷了我的饼干 还会有谁?
Yeah, well, if I've didn't take the cookies,
-我不知道… -嘿,吵什么!
Then, who the hell did?
I, I do not know ..
Hey!  Will you two morons knock it off!
我回家了
I'm going home.
…并覆盖着水,所以它可以存活生命
[On TV] .. covered in water and therefore able to sustain life.
我有更重要的事
I get more peace in the God-damned ape house.
爸爸,抱歉!
Dad, I'm sorry!
富兰克林先生,我是桃蒂!
Mr. Franklin, it's Dottie!
富兰克林先生?你在家吗?
Mr. Franklin? .. Hello?
我操 这什么情况?
What the hell?
朗尼,马上到平台来
[Over radio] Rodney, get to the platform, now.
朗尼!
[Over radio] Rodney!
你他妈的在想什么?
What the hell do you think you're doing, huh?
进去!
Get!
去啊!
Go on!
回笼子去!我警告你!
Get back in your cage!
I'm warning you!
去,去!
Go on, get!
对了!
That's it!
好受吗!你自找的!回去!
That's what you get! .. Get back!
服气吗?
What's wrong with you?
臭猴子!
Dumb monkey!
把你的臭手拿开,死猩猩!
Take your stinking paw off me, you damn dirty ape!
不!
No!
我要把你们全杀了!
I'll beat all!
卡洛琳,你在凯撒的房间吗?
Caroline, have you been up to Caesar's room?
没人听
No one's answering.
Landon!
兰登!
Will!
威尔!
发生了什么?
What happened?
他说话了
He spoke.
-什么? -你的猩猩…说话了
What are you .. what?
Your ape .. he spoke.
迷失太空?
发生了什么?简直不敢相信
What in the hell?
I don't believe this.
我把你们全杀了
[Video] I'll beat each and everyone of you.
我需要旧金山警局派一个法医来 告诉他,我们有一个受害者
I need someone to coordinate with the S.F.P.D.
Tell them we got a fatality.
-发生了什么? -我知道它要去哪里
What is it?
I know where he's headed.
Glenn?
格伦?
Let's go!
快走!
雅各
Jacobs.
雅各先生,我是琳达 这里发生了很可怕的事
[Cell phone] Mr. Jacobs, It's Linda from Will's team.
Look, something terrible has happened.
Franklin is dead from a viral infection.
富兰克林死了,死于病毒感染
What the hell are you talking about?
你在说什么?
He was exposed to the 113. It does something
是113型药物造成的 对于猿类是良药可对于人类是致命的
to people that it doesn't do to apes.
We'll have to go through the city and across the bridge.
它们会穿过小镇然后通过大桥
[Cell phone] Mr. Jacobs? Mr. Jacobs, are you ..
雅各先生?你在…
What the hell?
妈的怎么了?
I am Steven Jacobs!
我是雅各!
It's full of apes in there. I gotta get in the air!
那边全是猩猩 我要上直升机!
We have to be able to destroy them.
必须坐直升机转移了
Just, trust me on this! Okay?
相信我!
通常情况猩猩们都很害羞
You might want to get your cameras ready.  Normally,
these guys are quit shy.
-它们在公园北面! -在奔跑!
They're going  the park, on the north side!
Find the lead!
抓着扶手!
You gotta hold the button! The button!
它们在跑,这些猩猩比你想像的聪明
They're being led.  These apes are smarter than you think.
它们有一个首领!
They've got a leader!
不是,这里的交通堵住了 就没有精明点的吗
Do not tell them I am stuck in traffic. Make up with something smarter!
等等
Hold on.
那是什么…
What the ..
它们在桥上,这是要去红杉森林
They're on the bridge.
They're trying to get to the redwoods.
呼叫旧金山警局 这里是直升机
SFPD, Police 1.
This is Air Ops,
[On radio] Seal of south end. What's the status of those units?
封锁大桥南端 派出骑警部队
[Radio response] Ready to go, sir.
收到,长官
[On radio] As soon as they reach you, block them.
它们就快到你处 在北端布防
-呼叫北端 -没问题,我们布置好了
[On Radio] North side, we're going to push them right to you.
[Radio response] No problem. We're ready for them.
北端已经封锁
The north side is blocked. [On radio] They'll never get through here.
当它们到达开阔地 我们就开始清理!
As soon as they hit the gap, we'll take them out!
-你们想射击它们? -必须遏制在萌芽
You can just shoot them? Like shooting fish in a barrel.
好!
Good!
回去!别往这边走
Turn that thing around!
-请离开大桥,先生 -我明白…
Get off the bridge, sir. I can't ..
你不明白,离开大桥 这是紧急事件,快离开!
You don't understand. Get off this bridge, now!
This is an evacuation.  Get out!
各单位就绪
All the civilians, clear.
请求确认
[On radio] Please confirm.
把这些人带走!
Put these people off the bridge!
各单位做好准备!
Stand by, city mounted units!
将会有一场屠杀
They're gonna slaughter them.
我去找凯撒
I'm gonna to get Caesar.
听我说!
Will, hey!
You, be careful!
小心点!
I gotta get to my car!
-我要我的车! -离开那里!
Get out of here!
Let go me!  I have to get my car!
放开我!我要我的车!
Push 'em north!
北端部队!
Get out of the way!
让开!
快点  它们要消失在雾里了
Do It!
射击!
它们在哪里?我看不见!
Where are they?  I don't see them!
-北端部队,看见它们了吗? -还没有
[On radio] CHP North, do you have a visual?
No, sir, negative.
保险栓!
Safety's off!
停止射击!
Hold your fire!
Back!
撤退!
Caesar!
凯撒!
That's him!   That's the leader!
是它!它就是首领!
[On radio] They're in sight! Put 'em down!
Help me!
救我!
Take my hand!
抓住我的手!
Come, come on ..
拜托…
Come on!
拜托!
Not you ..
是你…
No!
不!
Save me!
救命!
Caesar!
凯撒!
Caesar?
凯撒?
Caesar .. I'm sorry.
凯撒…对不起,都是我不好
This is my fault.
This has to stop.
停下吧,这不是办法
This isn't the way.
You know what they're capable of.
你知道他们不会罢休
Please come home.
跟我回家吧
If you come home, I'll protect you.
你回家,我会保护你
Caesar is home.
凯撒已经回家了
Okay.
好吧
凯撒已经回家了
Caesar's home.
Go.
去吧!
（后面还有!别走开!）